<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The naked truth laid open, against vvhat is amiss: or, may be mis-interpreted, in those two bookes: the one, entituled, The foot out of the snare; and the other, The snare broken. Together with a word of invitation to all who are estranged to the true faith, that they would hear and receive the word of truth, which makes free the Israel of God. / Set forth by me John Toldervy.</title>
            <author>Toldervy, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94718</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1769</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E868_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207736</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866772</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866772</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119058</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94718)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119058)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 131:E868[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The naked truth laid open, against vvhat is amiss: or, may be mis-interpreted, in those two bookes: the one, entituled, The foot out of the snare; and the other, The snare broken. Together with a word of invitation to all who are estranged to the true faith, that they would hear and receive the word of truth, which makes free the Israel of God. / Set forth by me John Toldervy.</title>
                  <author>Toldervy, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>17 [i.e. 16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G. Calvert, at the Black-spread Eagle, at the West-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In reply to: Naylor, James.  Foot yet in the snare.</note>
                  <note>Pagination begins on verso of title page and continues with odd numbered pages on versos. Pages 8 and 9 skipped in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Febr: 21 1655"; also following the author statement: "A jugling knave".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Toldervy, John. --  Foot out of the snare --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Toldervy, John. --  Snare broken --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660. --  Foot yet in the snare --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119058:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NAKED TRUTH <hi>Laid open,</hi> Againſt vvhat is amiſs: <hi>OR,</hi> May be miſ-interpreted, <hi>IN THOSE</hi> TWO BOOKES: The one, entituled, <hi>The Foot out of the Snare;</hi> And the other, <hi>The Snare Broken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with a Word of Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to all who are eſtranged to the <hi>True Faith,</hi> that they would hear and receive the Word of Truth, which makes free the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of <hi>GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set forth by me <hi>John Toldervy.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rom. 9. 31, 32, 33.</bibl> But <hi>Iſrael</hi> which followed after the Law of Righteouſneſs, hath not attained to the Law of Righteouſneſs: Wherefore becauſe they ſought it not by Faith, but as it wore by the works of the Law, for they ſtumbled at that ſtumbling ſtone: As it is written, behold, I lay, in <hi>Sion</hi> a Stumbling ſtone, and a Rock of Offence; and whoſoever believeth on him ſhall not be aſhamed.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>G. Calvert,</hi> at the Black-ſpread Eagle, at the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119058:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Naked Truth laid open, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt what is amiſs, or may be miſ-interpreted, in theſe two Books: The one, entituled,</hi> The Foot out of the Snare: <hi>And the other,</hi> The Snare bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch, as there hath appeared ſome ſecreſie in me, in that work which firſt I appeared in to the World, entituled, <note n="†" place="margin">The Foot out of the Snare.</note> By which, the true end and ſcope of my purpoſe, in the greateſt part of what I have diſcovered, is much clouded in obſcurity from the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſight of men: and alſo, for that I have ſtood up in the Defence of this my Vanity, in that of <note n="†" place="margin">The Snare broken.</note> By which, much prejudice may attend that work, which the Prince of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is now in this our day bringing to paſſe, that his Name might be known in the Earth, a Deliverer from the Bonds of Iniquity, a Leader Captivity Captive, a Redeemer of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Choſen, which hath long lain in Death, by the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of a Rebellious people: I ſay, having not been found faithfull to that Witneſſe of God in my own Conſcience, which condemneth all deceit; and being much rebuked and condemned for what I have done, I am conſtrained in this further Diſcovery, that the Simple might be undeceived, and the Envious might be reproved.</p>
            <p>When firſt I was perſwaded to write, I had principally 4. things in my Eye: Firſt, my deſign was to diſcover the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptineſs, and the vanity of all that Miniſtry, and of all thoſe Ways, and Forms of Worſhip, which generally is upheld amongſt us by the dark mind of thoſe who are blind in their underſtandings; by which the people, who are in darkneſſe,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119058:2"/>
are mouriſhed in that condition, and the Seed of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, which creates a new heart, and redeems out of ſinne, is kept in bondage. And, for this purpoſe, I began with a Diſcovery of what I was, and how I was led, before I came amongſt thoſe people, who go under the name of <hi>Quakers.</hi> where, I ſay, <hi>I was for divers years full of zeal led forth in love to ſeek after the knowledge of God and Chriſt; for which cauſe I ſought, if that I could find, thoſe wayes and thoſe means, which were moſt uſeful for the clearing of my Conſcience, that I might walk in unity with God by a holy and innocent life: to which end,</hi> I ſaid <hi>(in my perſwaſion) I was led forth with much fervency of ſpirit, after thoſe teachers which were eſteemd of amongſt the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt Profeſſors, as men inlightned with the ſpirit of God: in which way I laboured, had there been a poſſibility to apprehend the true knowledge and mind of God: but not finding a poſſibility in that way, to apprehend the thing ſought for, but inſtead thereof, unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and diverſity of Opinions, confuſion in Societies, things which are at perfect enmity with God, who is one Spirit, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be divided;</hi> I ſaid, <hi>I left them as they were, and all that ever I received from them; and ſought further, if that I might find the way of Redemption, from under that heavy burthen, which lay upon me:</hi> in which ſeeking, (as I have ſpoken) <hi>I found ſuch who declared against all ſin whoſe order and manner of teaching, and Duties, were united, compleat in one, they being the fruits of one Mind by which they were joyned in one Spirit, and ſo judges and witneſſes for God, againſt all thoſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, who were going forth into the world, whoſe doctrine was of Man, who</hi> (having ſlain the Witneſs) <hi>knew not the Word of Life; therefore uncapable of edifying the People,</hi> and ſo <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Letter, and not of the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here, my purpoſe was, to extinguiſh them, who are ever learning the people, and themſelves, and yet never able to know the truth; and withall, to confirm thoſe who appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in ſuch a Witneſs againſt all ſin, <hi>whom I concluded were the people of God;</hi> whoſe doctrine and life, I have not denied [by words] in any particular, of all what I then diſcovered, except in thoſe things of civil Expreſſions, and Carriages, which otherwiſe I called Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>A ſecond thing, which my mind was directed in, was, to invite, or perſwade ſuch who were ſtrangers to thoſe people,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119058:3"/>
and their ways, who are called (of men) <hi>Quakers,</hi> That they ſhould inquire after that Truth which is profeſſed by them; for which end, I diſcovered them as ſuch who were <hi>united in one mind,</hi> and ſo <hi>acted on in their duties, whoſe Miniſtry was one, being guided therein by one Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. and then <hi>I relate a Diſcourſe miniſtred by one of thoſe people, with the effects which that Diſcourſe wrought upon my Spirit; together, with what I had received before from thoſe people;</hi> as the Diſcourſe holds ſoul; alſo <hi>of my orderly forbearance, untill I had received a more cleare underſtanding, before I complyed with them; in which time, I received a further Witneſs:</hi> And ſo I go on, <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering of their Judgment;</hi> without which knowledge, there is none can ever come to ſee the Redemption of their Souls. Theſe things being conſidered, I was perſwaded, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that end might be effected, for which purpoſe they were diſcovered.</p>
            <p>Having thus laid open my Underſtanding, I began in the third place, to give warning unto all, who may be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to receive the Word of Truth; that when convinced in their underſtandings, where that Word of Life, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deems out of ſinne, is to be found: That they conſider and examine in themſelves where withall they are led, that they run not before they are ſent, but to abide in the watch, that ſo they loſe not their Guide, and bring in Darkneſſe upon their Spirit: And for this cauſe, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, <hi>what evill attended me through the haſtineſs of my mind, in that I gave not heed to that obedience whereunto I was called; which evill I wholly took upon my ſelf, as being the work of myſelf:</hi> with purpoſe therein, to unvail that Darkneſſe, which was upheld, in many, by their miſ-underſtanding of the cauſe of thoſe things, which generally had paſſed abroad concerning me,</p>
            <p>A fourth end, was to diſcover thoſe things, practiſed by thoſe people who are in that way: in which I conceived there was no evill in the not performance thereof, And in reſpect of which things onely, I my ſelf did ſeparate from them, <hi>which things were none other, but a denial of thoſe things, which generally is called, Civil Carriage to Civil Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe four grounds, being the chiefeſt ends of my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in writing, I was wel ſatisfied in what work I had done,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119058:3"/>
though yet I appeared a tranſgreſſor (in reſpect to my ſelf) for which cauſe having received knowledge, that my ends are generally fruſtrated, I am conſtrained (as I have ſaid) in this further appearance to the world.</p>
            <p>Now that tranſgreſſion (in reſpect to my ſelf) was thus, in the conſideration of what condition I had brought my ſelf unto, ſince firſt I became affected with thoſe people, who are called of men Quakers: My minde was directed (as I have ſaid) for the anſwering of thoſe ends which I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, in which work I was glad; in that I was of any ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency to appear therein; but yet I would ſcarcely have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to the world, as one who ſhould diſcover himſelf in ſuch a work, that I might not be looked upon as one my ſelf, with thoſe people amongſt whom I was, leſt the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and loſſe of friendſhip from men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which once was my reward for the obedience of that faith, which the world knoweth not, I ſay, leſt ſelf ſhould thus have bin deſtroyed, I ſought ſecretly to diſcover my minde ſomething in obſcurity; but yet I made proviſion, that ſuch who were not ingaged, but would read and underſtand my witneſſe with a ſingle eye, that ſuch might ſee the end of my minde, according as before is diſcovered, which thing was unto me for the preſent, a ſatisfaction in what I had done.</p>
            <p>But yet further conſidering the ſtrangeneſs of that Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which declares of thoſe deluſions which the evill ſpirit in me guided me in ſubjection unto; and alſo conſidering what prejudice had befallen me by thoſe many reproaches which hath paſſed abroad concerning me, ſince my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from thoſe people: together, with what loſſe of kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and acquaintance had befallen me, ſince I came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: conſidering theſe things, I was much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked, time after time, to ſeek for ſome help, now in this my appearance to the world; but ſeeing this provocation was from the tempter, I was fully perſwaded for ſome time, after I had writ, that none ſhould have the leaſt ſight of what I had done, untill it was diſcovered to the world; but upon a further conſideration, that I might not appear ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous to men of ſerious mindes, becauſe of the ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of what I had related, I was perſwaded to deſire a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible witneſs of what I had ſo ſpoken, from ſome perſons of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119058:4"/>
ſober minds, whoſe moderation was ſomething known to me, though ſome there are, whoſe Names were made uſe of againſt my good-will,) but that the people for their ſakes, might not underſtand and otherwiſe then I intended, I was led forth to diſcover more plainly the cauſe of thoſe diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which I then declared, as the effect of the evil One in me: Before which diſcovery, I ſpake again of the darkneſſe, and the emptineſſe of that Miniſtry, which is of the outward Law of the Letter <hi>under which Miniſtry I could never enjoy a true peace,</hi> &amp;c. for which cauſe I ſaid, <hi>I departed from that way and Miniſtry having received knowledge where the truth indeed was to be found:</hi> which knowledge, I received from thoſe people before named; and ſo having related the effects, which this knowledge ſhould have wrought upon me, I came to diſcover how I erred from that work of Faith, wherein I was called, which firſt began with <hi>the Creatures Joy and Covenant and forward zeal, which ran before the fear, and ſo led forth before the true light, by which darkneſſe was brought in: in which Darkneſſe the Diſputer was raiſed to life, and exalted above the light of the Sonne formed in the ſhape of a true light; and ſo delight got the power by which the true obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was loſt, and ſo the Simple was deceived;</hi> and having thus done, I concluded in the praiſe of that way, in which thoſe people are led forth in, which leads to the perfect Truth; which way and truth is but one, which the world knoweth not: neither can they know, untill they come to walk in it.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being laid open, my Judgment was, that although thoſe names were uſed in my book, yet the people would have conſidered the thing, as it was diſcovered from me, and not in a generall ſence, as a thing proceeding from their Judgments, whoſe Names were unto it, and ſo another thing than it ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>But now I am miſtaken in my Judgment; and on the contrary, a Diviſion amongſt men concerning the thing, ſuch who are affected in the way of thoſe, whoſe Names appear in what I have done, they and theſe who have appeared, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to themſelves a ſatisfaction of that, which the thing ſpeaks not of, but condemns; as alſo it condemns them and their way.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119058:4"/>
A ſecond ſort there are, in whom there is no prejudice unto the one, or unto the other, but receives the thing as it is ſingly, and they give witneſs, that ſurely a thing could not have appeared more (in ſuch a caſe as this was) on the behalf of thoſe people, who go under the name of Quakers, than that did. And a third ſort have been unſatisfied, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whether it ſpeaks for the one, or for the other.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I received knowledge of, time after time, from divers whoſe mindes were thus different in the thing: but in the conſideration, that there were ſuch who ſaw my minde, and meaning as it was, and ſo received my witneſſe. I aboad hitherto ſilent, judging, that if ſuch who were inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, would leave their vanity, they might ſee and underſtand as others did: and that ſuch, who ſay they could not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the true meaning thereof, might leave the thing as it was.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>James Naylor,</hi> that perſon from whom there was diſcovered in anſwer unto the thing, by what I now am gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to underſtand, was otherwiſe minded, in reſpect of ſome things, than what I at firſt underſtood of him, which was thus. When having read his Book, and ſeeing much of the Spirit of Judgment upon me, and all thoſe who appeared with me, and that we were by him united in one, as ſuch who were joyned in enmity againſt the light of Chriſt; and that he looked upon them as one with me, and I with them, in the whole of what was diſcovered, and ſo ſecret ſmiters againſt the truth: the thing being ſomething in obſcurity-Seeing theſe things, I was moved, and ſought to finde what ſhould be the cauſe why he appeared in ſuch a Spirit; for I ſaw that either he was much miſtaken, or elſe I was greatly deceived in what I had done; but when having ſearched a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and again, I could not ſee that his judgment was true upon me, except in that, of my receiving other witneſſe to what I had diſcovered than my own: the extent of which deed, I ſaw, as to me, little evill in; for that I had diſcovered my Witneſſe, according as I have before related, in which, if well conſidered, there was no advantage for them, or any that might affect them: Neither could I ſee his Judgment to be true, in ſome things, concerning thoſe who appeared
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119058:5"/>
with me, in that; he concluded them as one with me in what I had done &amp; as privy to what was contained in the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or the Epiſtle. Now theſe things being ſo by what I knew concerning their knowledge of the Title, or the Epiſtle, or could apprehend concerning the other, I was much troubled concerning him, and that work he appeared in: upon which, I conſidered with my ſelf what I were beſt to do, if to return an anſwer, or if to let it reſt ſilent: in which conſideration, (my ſpirit being moved) I was perſwaded to return an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: for as yet I was diſpleaſed, in that I ſaw my deſigns were wholly broken in many things, which in obſcurity I had diſcovered with purpoſe to advance the truth (though I would ſcarcely have been ſeen in ſo doing) and ſo I was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as a perſon unworthy, and my work, as confuſion, though other things, ſpoken in more plainneſs, appeared for me as a true Witneſs.</p>
            <p>Now, having ſome advantage for the effecting of this work, and the more, by ſome clouded expreſſions; which yet being diſcovered as my mind, that the Juſt might not be condemned, I was therein ſatisfied, and ſo directed in a dir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle anger againſt the perſon <hi>James Naylor,</hi> though (at the preſent) I thought I was guided therein, by obedience to the Juſt in me, in that I made ſome proviſion to ſecure the people and their way, though I judged his perſon, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned his deed: But when after, what I had thus done was publiſhed to the world, my mind being ſetled; in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of them ſeriouſly, I was ſmitten in my judgment, and much reproved, for that I ſaw an envious ſpirit had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in me: Then was there given me clearly to ſee the right mind in which <hi>James Naylor</hi> was led, in the anſwering what I had diſcovered: by which I ſaw, truly, much of what he ſpake, to be another thing, then what I formerly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and his Judgments, in a great meaſure, to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in truth; for, in that I ſpake in obſcurity, <hi>I</hi> ſaw <hi>I</hi> laid a ſtumbling block before the truth; and in that <hi>I</hi> engaged others, this my obſcurity became a ſnare to thoſe, by whom they were affected: and ſo <hi>I</hi> receiving their teſtimony, though not one with them in the thing, nor they one with me: yet in reſpect of the end, which is effected by their means, <hi>I</hi> was overcome, and ſo became one with them, in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119058:5"/>
that end which the thing it ſelf doth condemn: And thus (through my vanity) we all became ſecret ſmiters againſt the truth; which things being made known, <hi>I</hi> could do no leſs but diſcover that the burden of my ſpirit might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and that the Juſt might not ſuffer by my meanes, knowing there is a time in which all ſecrets ſhall be laid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and every deed ſhall receive its own reward: Therefore have <hi>I</hi> rather choſen to own the Condemnation, that the truth might have its free courſe without interruption, and to paſs by what reproach might be caſt upon me, for that <hi>I</hi> have appeared herein, knowing that unto the truth <hi>I</hi> am made manifeſt, by whom <hi>I</hi> am witneſſed, that if by any means <hi>I</hi> could have put by this work, <hi>I</hi> ſhould have been much glad (with reſpect to my ſelf) therein: But where the blame is, my due, I muſt receive it (from all) as my due, and therein reſt ſilent: And for that deed of engaging the Miniſters, I am ſorry (as I have ſaid) that I ſhould be ſo fooliſhly led forth as I was therein, both in reſpect to them, and alſo to the thing in hand, by which my whole purpoſe (having appeared ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in obſcurity) generally became void, and ſo deceived my ſelf and them alſo.</p>
            <p>But now I would freely ſpeak my mind, and utter words in knowledge, that the juſt might receive its own due; yet not in the leaſt envy, with reſpect to one or the other; but in plainneſſe, as I have received: Therefore, my deſire is, that none would receive to themſelves any offence in this work: but if in any, (as I have before ſaid) in what formerly I have done; for verily (as I have ſpoken) often-times I was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in ſeeking in thoſe ways, which the primeſt Profeſſors of theſe Times, who were led by the Letter, were guided in, I ran from one to another, from Mountain to Hill, I ſought to find, but could not: onely I increaſed in wiſdome (the work of my own labour) and this wiſdome, being of the fleſh, was pleaſant and delightful, and ſo I thought it was the Myſtery of the Spirit: But yet ſtill this wiſdome was unto me but little ſatisfaction, though I laboured very ſtrictly in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to what I had learned from the Law of the Letter, which was the end of that Miniſtry, by which I was guided; for there was ſomething yet in me that was unſatisfied, which lay under a great burthen, which all the wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119058:6"/>
in my ſelf, and in thoſe my Learners, was not, in the leaſt, able to ſatisfie: Yet, in that time, I could not ſee the cauſe of theſe things; but when after I came to hear thoſe people who are called (of men) <hi>Quakers,</hi> in a ſhort time I was clearly convinced, and given to ſee, the end of all my former labours, and the cauſe of my troubled ſpirit: for they being redeemed out of the wiſdome, out of the imaginations of the brain, which is ſenſual, and of the fleſh, &amp;c. they ſpake by and from that Spirit of Life in them, by which they were redeemed; and ſo their words, being from the Life, reached to the Life, the Seed of the Righteous, which lay under the dark Mind burdened, and groaning for a deliverance. And here was that Myſtery that is of God, <hi>which miniſters to the Spirits in Priſon:</hi> Which being made known, I was not in the leaſt able to gain-ſay: And then I ſaw, indeed, that <hi>Word of Faith which reveals the everlaſting Goſpel</hi> to be <hi>near in the Mouth and in the Heart;</hi> and that <hi>Circumciſion which is of God, was of the heart, in the Spirit, and not in the Letter; whoſe praiſe was not of Man, but of God.</hi> But now for any to judge, that all, or any of thoſe diſtractions, and workes of deceit, which are delcared by me, as the effects of my diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the light; I ſay, for any to judge of them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than they are, and to caſt them as a reproach upon the light, it is vain and evill, and a thing contrary to my whole mind: for that (as I have ſpoken) I dare not, neither can I ſay, but that the whole cauſe of all thoſe evils, was of my ſelf: But though my ſufferings was great, when after I came in this way, yet I ſaw much good was the end of all, Peace and Reſt in Spirit, according to the meaſure of Grace recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, which I never could ſee or attain unto, by all thoſe means, and in all thoſe ways which formerly I was led forth in: But to ſpeak in truth (that the Juſt might receive its own) wherein I have at any time with-drawn from that grace I then lived in, therein I have refuſed the good, and choſe the evill, which works I muſt acknowledge, as the works of my ſelf in the hour of judgment.</p>
            <p>And now, I hope that none will judge of me, as an Offence to the Law of Righteouſneſſe, but as one that eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Law in Righteouſneſſe (though much againſt my own ſelf-will) and have I choſen to acknowledge that thing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119058:6"/>
which is rejected of amongſt men, becauſe my Conſcience beareth me witneſſe, and ſeals to the truth thereof? I hope men will not be ſo vain to deny, but that I have moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in thus doing. I honour and reſpect all men, as they are men: but ſhould I honour and reſpect that in man, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their Miniſtry, or Practice; which I know aſſuredly in my own Conſcience, is not of God, but of themſelves: I ſay verily, ſhould I do ſo, I ſhould be condemned of my ſelf, and for that deed of mine, in engaging other perſons then my ſelf in what I formerly did, I looked otherwiſe upon the thing then it did effect: my mind was principally to receive a civill favour from them (with reſpects to my ſelf, as I have before ſpoken) and not for the diſhonour of the wayes of Truth: And for that I appeared in enmity to thoſe things diſcovered by <hi>James Naylor,</hi> againſt that end, which their appearance with me hath accompliſhed, for that I ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, I was miſtaken: For now I ſee his mind was one and the ſame with what firſt was in me: wherefore, I can no leſs but deny that my miſtake, and receive the Judgment which I did for ſo doing caſt upon him, as due unto my ſelf; and did I in diſpleaſure call him a falſe Prophet, Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a body of deceit, &amp;c. I muſt unſpeak what I ſo ſpake, and deny my ſelf therein: Yet however, my mind was what <hi>I</hi> ſo called him, to extend no further then the thing in hand, for <hi>I</hi> knew another life in him, whoſe name is true, by whom the whole body of darkneſs in all the ways of ſelf-worſhip amongſt men is ſeen, judged, and condemned: and for thoſe things of which I ſpake in my firſt book though in obſcurity, (with purpoſe that I might be excuſed in the ſight of men) which were diſcovered in judgment upon me, by one of thoſe people amongſt whom I was, by which I was denied as one of them, when firſt I departed from them, that the light of truth might be left inexcuſable, I muſt confeſs the judgment (in a great meaſure) there in was true, I was fallen from that by which I was convinced, which was the life of righteouſnes in ſpirit, &amp; in power, which being ſeen by thoſe who abode in the faith, <hi>I</hi> was refuſed in ſo doing, (though yet unto that eye with which the Profeſſors of the world are led, <hi>I</hi> ſhould not have appeared a tranſgreſſor) and when it was ſeen of me that light in my Conſcience, unto which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119058:7"/>
was diſcovered, was made manifeſt, was one with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the thing diſcovered, ſo that I had not a word for my ſelf, when the witneſſe was made known unto me.</p>
            <p>Yet as to thoſe things which <hi>I</hi> called the fruits of Civility, and indifferent things, in which I declared, there was no ſin, <hi>I</hi> ſaw not at that time, neither do <hi>I</hi> yet ſee (if uſed in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration) that evill is the cauſe in the practice of them, yet however, ſeeing my weakneſs, I will not be much confident concerning them, though my Conſcience at the preſent may not condemn them, neither would <hi>I</hi> that any ſhould follow my example therein, except they ſee a freedom in themſelves; for a time was when all the world could not have perſwaded me in the practices of any of them, my Conſcience being my witneſs in defence againſt all the perſwaſions of man &amp; now whether <hi>I</hi> have erred or no, I know not. When firſt <hi>I</hi> layed them down, it was in the obſervation of others, and not by any Command <hi>I</hi> ſaw in my ſelfe; but when after ſome time of my continuance, in the way and work whereunto <hi>I</hi> was called, <hi>I</hi> was verily perſwaded, that all thoſe things <hi>I</hi> layed down in the imitation, was not then performed in the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; but by a Command from the witneſs raiſed in me, in my own Conſcience; but when <hi>I</hi> was guided to take them up again, (as <hi>I</hi> have ſpoken) <hi>I conſidered the firſt cauſe by which I was led in the laying of them down;</hi> and finding the deed was wrought in my will, (being in the imitation) <hi>I</hi> was a little provoked to take them up again, and the rather, becauſe <hi>I</hi> ſaw no place of Scripture, which directly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, though <hi>I</hi> could not ſee any practice of them, by (any, who appeared in Scripture: which perſwaſion for the preſent, for what <hi>I</hi> can ſay, was out of knowledge, though at fifth <hi>I</hi> laid them down in the imitation; but when <hi>I</hi> had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them up for a little time, my ſpirit was free in the uſing of them, as though <hi>I</hi> never had denyed them; and now if <hi>I</hi> have done well, <hi>I</hi> know not, but if evill, <hi>I</hi> muſt once again know the Judgement.</p>
            <p>Theſe things was I moved to write, not out of evill, with reſpect to one, or unto other perſon or thing, yea truly I have not in the leaſt been partiall towards my ſelf, but my whole minde were directed, that I might remove the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of my ſpirit; and freely out of good will towards men,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119058:7"/>
and that for the ſake of truth, whoſe light is made known, that men might ſee and underſtand the things that belong unto their peace: now in this day of everlaſting love. And now what ſhall I ſay of my ſelf? have I appeared an evill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, one toſſed to and fro, led aſide by vanity, a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to the Lord, and his wayes of truth and righteouſneſſe, a ſtumbling block to the ſimple, an offence to all, have I thus done? I am diſquieted with my ſelf, and good had it been, that theſe things had not been ſo; but now in that I have thus done, as I deny my ſelf therein, ſo alſo I ſhould deſire, that none would therein receive me; but in that I have here ſpoken the words of truth, as they are in the truth (though much againſt my will) ſuffer me a little, that I may prevail in that I have thus done.</p>
            <p>The Scriptures they declare of the minde of God, and of the practice of the Saints, in which there is made known the whole Law, by which ſo far as men are ſubjected unto it, they are found in the moderation, in temperance, in chaſtity, in a degree of faithfulneſs to God and to man; and this is good; but yet man (being fallen from God) is not redeemed by this obedience of the outward Law, into that ſtate from whence he is fallen, as it is written, <hi>But that no man is juſtified by the Law, in the ſight of God,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>it is evident, for the juſt ſhall live by faith, and the Law is not of faith, but the man that doth them, ſhall live in them;</hi> but the Scriptures they declare of him, who is the Redeemer, and where he is to be ſound; but they are not him, <hi>which is in the month, and in the heart, the word of faith. Moſes</hi> was a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, but he was not the Chriſt. Chriſt Jeſus appeared in the viſible, and was true in himſelf, yet the ſpirit was not given untill he was glorified: Now that Law that is of faith in the ſpirit, that judges and condemns the Serpent, in the root whence he ſprang, which faith, whomſoever receives, will ſee that promiſed ſeed which breaketh the head of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, to be neare <hi>in the month, and in the Heart;</hi> and ſo the miniſtration of death being paſſed upon the unjuſt, the ſpirit is renewed untill the election be raiſed to life, unto which the promiſe is two, and ſo that ſtate witneſſed, of which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake to the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> the third and the third; <hi>For ye are dead, and Your life is bid with Chriſt in God,</hi> by which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119058:8"/>
obedience the ſpirit is renewed, they being the fruits of faith, <hi>There is therefore now no condemnation to them</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>which are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit; for the Law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made me free from the Law of ſin and death, <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 23. 24.</note> But before Faith came, we were kept under the Law, ſhut up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Faith, which ſhould afterwards be revealed: wherefore the Law was our Schoolmaſter, to bring us unto Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by faith;</hi> but now they that are not yet come to the hearing of faith are ſtrangers to theſe things, <hi>Paul</hi> was very ſtrict in this profeſſion: as touching his Converſation amongſt men blameleſs, <hi>he profited in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 14.</note> the Jewiſh Religion above many his equalls, being more exceedingly zealous, of the Traditions of the Fathers;</hi> yet all this while he was a ſtranger to the true faith, <hi>until it pleaſed God to reveal his Son in him;</hi> and thus it is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 1. 516.</note> with all who are led by the letter, untill they come to ſee Chriſt Jeſus brought to light in them; yet ſhould I ſay, there is no other way under Heaven, by which men can come to know their Redeemer, but by that light, with which all are inlightened, Chriſt Jeſus the light of the World, ſhould I ſo ſay as <hi>I</hi> do, vanity and darknes unto which what I ſo ſpeak is unknown, would deny me in ſo ſpeaking; but my words are true, by which I may not be deceived, knowing they come forth, from the word of truth, <hi>I</hi> have a little taſted of both wayes, of the good, and of the evill; but really <hi>I</hi> found the <hi>fooliſhneſs of preaching,</hi> to be another thing then the <hi>wiſdom of fleſh, and baſe things, and things of mean degree,</hi> to be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, then what is in the <hi>exaltation,</hi> though never ſo lovely; but here is the miſery, darkneſs is paſſed over, and ſo good is called evill, and evill good: let not people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve generall reports, but call to minde a deſpiſed people, thoſe were they in all generations; but if any thing heard and ſeen in particular, may appear truly to be evill, then may it be refuſed; but if good, why then are men ſo vain, that they will not ſee, that ſo they may underſtand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> was taken from his <hi>firſt Habitation, and from his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. 5.</note> kindred,</hi> and ſent <hi>by revelation into a strange Land,</hi> in which obedience he received the promiſes: now <hi>the promiſes are made unto the ſeed, not as of many, but as of one, which ſeed is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 16.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119058:8"/>
               <hi>Chriſt. I will bleſs them that bleſſe thee, &amp; curſe them that curſe thee, and in thee ſhall all the Families of the Earth be bleſſed,</hi> not as of <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> but of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> neither yet <hi>not of the Law but of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. 3. 21. 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 18.—3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 10.</note> 
               <hi>promiſe;</hi> but <hi>the Law was added becauſe of tranſgreſſion, untill the ſeed ſhould come unto whom the promiſe was made,</hi> againſt which inheritance there is no Law, as it is written, <hi>but the word of the Oath which was ſince the Law, maketh the Son which is conſecrated for evermore,</hi> and here is it now not of works, but of grace.</p>
            <p>Man being run out from God into the <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,</hi> he hath broken the <hi>Law,</hi> the fruit was <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant</hi> and <hi>delightful,</hi> he feels tis <hi>pleaſant, (the daughters of men were fair)</hi> and now he knowes <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evill,</hi> he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Curſe,</hi> he <hi>hides himſelf,</hi> he is <hi>aſhamed,</hi> and thus (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving denyed the obedience required, <hi>death is paſſed over that ſeed created by God in him a living ſoul,</hi> and ſo that breath of life which came forth from God, and breaths after himſelf <hi>is hid in darkneſs,</hi> and now being loſt in this fallen eſtate, the ſame nature in him, which at firſt joyned with the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, feeding upon the Tree of knowledge, ſeeks for a juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication (having transformed it ſelf into the outward forms of worſhip and appearances of things) and thus the eye with which men ſhould ſee, being put out, the evill day is put a farre off, and the good day rejected.</p>
            <p>But now the <hi>Grace of God hath appeared,</hi> by which is made <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 18, 19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 16. 17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 8, 9.</note> known the everlaſting Goſpel of Peace but yet who <hi>hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved our report. So then faith commeth by hearing, and hearing by the word of God</hi> which <hi>word is near in the mouth, and in the heart,</hi> and here is the end of the Covenant, <hi>That if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and believe in thy heart that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi> Now to confeſs with the <hi>mouth,</hi> and believe with the <hi>heart,</hi> is not onely a belief in the minde, what the Scriptures declare of him, <hi>that he is riſen,</hi> and ſo a confeſsion from that belief; but to confeſs &amp; believe to the <hi>Reſurrection of him in us to increaſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 1. 2. 19. 12. 2.—23.</note> 
               <hi>with the increaſe of God;</hi> to the <hi>death</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection of Chriſt,</hi> above <hi>the rudiments of the world,</hi> and the <hi>Ordinances, which things have a ſhadow of the wiſdom,</hi> and ſo to witneſs what <hi>David</hi> ſpake, <hi>I know my Redeemer liveth,</hi> and what <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake <hi>I live, yet not I but Jeſus Chriſt that liveth in me.</hi> And now what redeems but the precious <hi>blood of Chriſt, as of a Lamb</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 9.</note>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119058:9"/>
(in all) <hi>from the foundation of the world:</hi> and this Redemption, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5: 10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 21 <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 8.</note> 
               <hi>is perfock</hi> into the ſtate in which man was firſt created, unto which <hi>there is no death,</hi> by which regeneration, ſuch who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the power for the obedience of the faith in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>boing born again of him, are become the ſeed of Abraham,</hi> and ſo <hi>inhenitors of the promiſes,</hi> by Generation, and here is the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> Chriſt Jeſus brought forth into the World; but this is a Myſtery to ſuch whoſe mindes are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, who are yet ſeeking for a Chriſt without, whoſe faith is without, whoſe obedience is without, who are eſtranged from the diſcovery of Chriſt Jeſus within, who is given <hi>of the Father, to work all our works in as, and through us, that the praiſe might be alone of him that calloth;</hi> but now <hi>it is of grace,</hi> and not <hi>by any works of righteouſneſs, which we have done, but through the obedience of faith in him,</hi> which is not of the will; but by which the leaſt motion to will is ſubdued, in its motion, which is wrought in ſpirit, by obedience to the ſpirit, for the Reſurrection of the ſeed, which things the Adultreſs eye cannot ſee; but unto thoſe that have received the light, they are made manifeſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119058:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
